<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A review of the Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses written by A Gentleman of Quality.</title>
            <author>Diggs, Dudley, 1613-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1459</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12179258</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12179258</idno>
            <idno type="VID">197172</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21237)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 197172)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 244:E97, no 1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A review of the Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses written by A Gentleman of Quality.</title>
                  <author>Diggs, Dudley, 1613-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Dudley Diggs. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>This defense of the divine right of kings, in reply to Henry Parker's "Observations", 1642 has been attributed to Diggs by DWB and Wood-Bliss, Athenae Oxonienses, but the attribution is doubted by Madan on reasonable grounds and is not to be confused with Digg's "An answer to a printed book", 1642.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652. --  Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:197172:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:197172:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A REVIEW</hi> OF THE OBSERVATIONS UPON SOME OF HIS MAjESTIES late Anſwers <hi>and Expreſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by a Gentleman <hi>of Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD, <hi>Printer to the Vniverſity.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:197172:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:197172:2"/>
            <head>A REVIEW OF THE Obſervations upon ſome of His <hi>Majeſties late Anſwers and Expreſſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Conteſtation between Regall and Parliamentary authority, finding by the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Declarations of the two Honourable Houſes made unto the People, (like ſo many Appeales of the Body repreſentative, to the Body at large,) that the Soveraign judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all things is (upon the matter) brought unto the People, I ſee not, but that it is both lawfull, and even the neceſſary duty of every private man, that hath any underſtanding of the things in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, to publiſh his particular judgement &amp; apprehenſion of them; That from the moſt free and univerſall agitation of the truth, ſome judgement from that vaſt body may be rendered to the appealors ſatisfaction. And ſo, having conceived that the Author of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon His Majeſties late Anſwers, hath upon this ſubject broached divers State-doctrines, neither agreeable to our Lawes, nor yet to true Chriſtian Religion: and that yet, (to the prejudice of the Truth,) they have, as truths, got a ſtrong prepoſſeſſion of men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mindes; I have thought fit to offer ſuch notions upon the ſumme of them, as I conceive ought to bring them to a more ſerious re-exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Saving therefore to His Majeſty His Right of Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into the particular <hi>falſities, inſolences,</hi> and <hi>ſeditious calumnies</hi> in the ſeverall paſſages of that booke; I only apply my ſelfe to the ſumme and ſcope thereof, and that I find to be to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That God is no more Author of Regall power then of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocraticall, and as much Author of uſurped Dominion as of Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. That Power is originally inherent in the People, and but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivative
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:197172:3"/> in Kings. That the People are the efficient and finall cauſe of Kings. That the name of King is not greater then of People. That though the King be <hi>ſingulis major,</hi> yet He is <hi>univerſis minor.</hi> That He is not to be accounted a God, a King, a Lord, a Father <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the People <hi>conjunctim,</hi> but <hi>diviſim</hi> only. That Treaſon (ſo farre as it concernes the Prince) is not ſo horrid in nature, as oppreſſion in a Prince, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the better examining of theſe, we finde; That God creating man ſingle, left him not other meanes of multiplying, then only by propagation, and in propagating, he gave the Rule and Soveraignty of the iſſues propagated, to the Father of whom they were propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and in defailance of the Father, He gave the Rule of all the younger (and conſequently of their deſcendants too) unto the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> (as we may ſee where God tells <hi>Caine; Thy Brother ſhall be ſubject to thee, and thou ſhalt beare rule over him.</hi> So that all men in the beginning were born Subjects, either to him that naturally was their Father, or to him that by right of primogeniture was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatively the Father. After the Flood, the then common Father of the world, having a family of three Sonnes of differing condition, and they (for the plantation of the then unpeopled world) by Gods determinate fore-councell diſperſed into three diſtant parts of it, the elder Brothers right of Soveraignty over thoſe younger, (through diſtance of place, and want of occaſion and meanes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe it.) became wholy neglected, as upon like ſeverance and ſearch of new places of Plantation, it, in other places, often after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came. But every Planter becomming ſo by himſelfe a Father, ſoon became a Family, and from a Family grew into a Citty, ſo into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Cities, and at length into a Kingdome. And though we firſt heare of the irregular Kingdome of the deſcendant of <hi>Cham,</hi> yet find we alſo, that <hi>Shem</hi> the eldeſt and bleſſed Sonne of thoſe three, was grown into the Soveraignty of a Kingdome, and was the firſt King that ever was in the world: for by the judgement and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the Learned, <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> the King of <hi>Salem,</hi> could be no other then very <hi>Shem</hi> himſelfe. Neither had the tenne Tribes of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> (when revolting from the ſonne of <hi>David,</hi> they ſaid, <hi>they had no part in</hi> David, <hi>nor Portion in the ſonne of</hi> Ieſſe,) any other meaning then only to inferre; That <hi>David</hi> being neither their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>nature,</hi> nor in primogeniture by <hi>repreſentation,</hi> they were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:197172:3"/> free from that naturall ſubjection unto his ſonne, which otherwiſe (they implied) they were bound to be ſubject to. And indeed, (if there had not been an eſpeciall ordinance of God in the caſe) it had truly followed; that being neither deſcended of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> nor <hi>Ieſſe</hi> the firſt borne of their common Father; the rule of ſubiection which followed nature, had not tyed them to obey his ſonne. The fifth Commandement it ſelfe proveth this naturall bond of ſubiection, when (as all Churches expound it) it commands <hi>Obedience</hi> to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, under the name of Parents only. And that (according to Gods ſaying unto <hi>Caine) Soveraignty</hi> did rightfully follow <hi>primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniture,</hi> we may ſee it in this; that as God promiſed <hi>Iacob</hi> the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty,</hi> ſo he procured him the <hi>Birth-right,</hi> formally tranſacted by <hi>Eſaus</hi> ſale of it. Therefore a King being no other then a common Father, by either <hi>naturall</hi> or <hi>legall</hi> Right; neither the People, nor any other Power then only God (the Father of nature it ſelfe) can properly be ſaid to be the author of the being of Kings.</p>
            <p>Next, God hath not authorized Kingly Power in nature only; but by his expreſſe promiſes before the law, and by his ordinances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, in the law, even before ever the people of <hi>Iſraell</hi> ſought a King: alſo by ſetling over his People the government of a King: by ſacrating that office with <hi>annointing:</hi> by his own aſſuming of the name of King: and by ſetting forth our Saviours Dominion over his Church, by that name and office. In all which if God hath done the like for authorizing <hi>ariſtocraticall</hi> or <hi>vſurped</hi> Dominion; then is the Obſervour in thoſe <hi>aſſertions</hi> to be juſtified: but if not, then is he in them an Author of lyes. Yea, God is more Author of what he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines and directs, then of what he only permits; and therefore more Author of good, then of evill. Wherefore to ſay <hi>vſurped</hi> Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on referres as much to God as author thereof, as lawfull <hi>hereditary</hi> Dominion doth, is not only falſe but alſo blaſphemous.</p>
            <p>As for Power inherent in the People, how ſhould one imagine ſuch a thing? unleſſe alſo he would imagine People to be <hi>juvenes aquilone creati,</hi> men like <hi>graſhoppers</hi> and <hi>locuſts</hi> bred of the winde, or like <hi>Cadmus</hi> his men ſprung out of the earth; where none deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from any pre-exiſtent Parents, had all of them equall originall and power, and therefore ſubject to no civill Power but what by agreement they themſelves ordained? But where man is borne of a Father, to whom, by the law of God and nature he is ſubject, he is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:197172:4"/> ſo farr from having inherent Power originally in him, as that he hath not his own originall being but only in ſubjection; either to his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Father, if his Father were abſolute, or to him and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Father, if his Father were a Subject. Now if man, in his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and naturall capacity, hath not originall Power of himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in him, he cannot have originall inherent Power, by any civill capacity whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And though, upon the overthrow and breaking up of Kingdomes, inſtance may perhaps be given; that People have made themſelves a King, yet does not that prove, the People to be the originall of Kingly Power; no more th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n going upon crutches, after loſſe of a legg, proves crutches the originall and naturall way of going: for people being by misfortune deprived of their naturall common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Soveraign, muſt of neceſſity entertaine ſuch ſupply of their loſſe, as their fortune can beſt afford them. And even in that caſe too, their making of a King, was no other, then the chooſing of one to beare the known Office of the true and naturall common Father. For we muſt note, they never made Kings by giving them power <hi>conſtitutive,</hi> to doe ſo; and ſo; (as they muſt have done, if Kings had had nothing but commiſſionary authority from the people,) but they made Kings, only by chooſing one to beare the office and perſon of the ſame Governour, that the law of nature had before deſcribed and authorized to command and governe.</p>
            <p>Though therefore the ten Tribes of <hi>Iſraell</hi> rebelled againſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam,</hi> for refuſing to releive their greivance, made <hi>Ieroboam</hi> King, and God forbad <hi>Rehoboam</hi> to warre againſt them for it, yet this proves not, That people have power of making Kingdoms or Kings. For God himſelfe had firſt declared, that he would rend ten Tribes from the Kingdome of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and that <hi>Ieroboam</hi> ſhould be King over them. And had <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and the people attended Gods will and pleaſure in it, (as <hi>David</hi> after his annointing did) he had beene a King and they a Kingdome not of their own making but of Gods. But to ſhew how quickly the by-affections of the people pervert the right work of God, when they looke not as well unto the way, as unto the end: we may ſee, that for all this, new Kingdome &amp; King were of Gods appointing, yet when the people would in a way of their owne, take upon them the Crowning of the man appointed, God diſclaimes the authorizing of what they did. <hi>They ſet up a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:197172:4"/> King</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>but not by me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea. 8.4.</note> and in recording the fact (both in the firſt of <hi>Kings,</hi> and againe in the ſecond of <hi>Chronicles</hi>) the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture directly telleth us, that they rebelled. That therefore God forbad <hi>Rehoboam</hi> to fight againſt them, did not approve what the people had done, for God tells the reaſon why he forbad them; not becauſe the people had done well, but becauſe the thing was of God, which if God had not revealed, <hi>Rehoboam</hi> might, and ought to have reduced them to their obedience: and howſoever the thing it ſelfe was of God, yet to teach us, that the people have not autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to doe the thing that he hath ordained, without his eſpceiall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, we ſee that when <hi>Abijah, (Rehoboams</hi> ſonne) with foure hundred thouſand, againſt eight hundred thouſand, pitched a battle upon the right of that Kingdome, and committed the cauſe to God, though <hi>Ieroboam</hi> had entrapped him in an ambuſh, God gave ſuch a ſentence againſt <hi>Ieroboam</hi> and his people, that after an overthrow and ſlaughter of five hundred thouſand of them, they were diſabled from ever recovering ſtrength in all <hi>Abijahs</hi> dayes. And that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for luck ſake may take heed of making new Kingdomes, or Kings: this King (the only inſtance of peoples King-making, and yet in making of whom the people did only anticipate Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed work) became the inſtrumentall efficient of their finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, &amp; (ſetting up the Idolatry which the people themſelves had firſt affected) his ſinne through all his ſucceſſours ſo adhered to them, as that it never left them, untill it had extirpated them from their own, and transferred them captives into another Country. To conclude this point, when we heare God himſelfe ſtiling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a <hi>King,</hi> a great <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and telling us that <hi>the Kingdome is the Lords,</hi> &amp;c: who without reluctance of conſcience and even horrour of it, can yeild the power of Kings to be <hi>derivative,</hi> and the People to be the <hi>originall</hi> of it? for then, God by ſetting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe forth in the name of a King, does inſtead of preſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in a notion of <hi>magnificence</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> preſent himſelfe under the notion of an <hi>inferiour</hi> and of a <hi>derivative,</hi> from a more <hi>Soveraigne</hi> and <hi>originall</hi> Power: whereas we ſee God never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes his Power by the name of an Elder, or of a Magiſtrate, or any ſubordinate Authority how good or honourable ſoever. Yea to be <hi>King of Kings,</hi> is then no more, then to be the <hi>derivative</hi> and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Kings.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:197172:5"/>
            <p>As for the Peoples being the efficient and finall cauſe of the King. If one knew in what ſence the Obſervour would be underſtood, he were ſoone anſwered. For if he would be underſtood according to the propriety of his wordes, (as indeed that which he would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine does need he ſhould,) Then is that poſition not only falſe, but an impious falſhood, even full blaſphemy: for properly God, and none but God, is the efficient and finall cauſe of all things: there being no difference betweene the efficient cauſe and the Creatour. But if the Obſervour means, that the people be the inſtrumentall cauſe of Kings; the inſtrumentall cauſe and mediate end, are termes of ſo extreame and notorious difference, and conſequence, from effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and finall cauſe, as it is by no meanes to be pardoned him that he ſhould meane the one, and ſay the other. Beſides, to underſtand him ſo, does overthrow all that he drives at: for if the People be but the inſtrumentall cauſe of Kings, then can they not be the end of Kings, no more then the inſtrument of any worke can be the end for which the work was made, but contrarily the work is the end of the inſtrument, and therefore greater then the inſtrument. As for the people, they are ſo farre from being the finall end of Kings, as that they are not any way the end of them. For government is the end of Kings (of which the People are but the Subject) and God alone is both the efficient cauſe and finall end, both of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Governour, and Subject to be governed.</p>
            <p>As for that which he affirmes, That though Kings be <hi>ſingulis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jores</hi> yet are they <hi>vniverſis minores,</hi> and that wherein ſoever they be to be accounted. <hi>Gods, Lords, Fathers, Heads,</hi> unto the People; they are not ſo to be underſtood, otherwiſe then as to the particular perſons of men, conſidered <hi>ſingly</hi> not <hi>jointly,</hi> what an impudent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence is it that one that has uſe of reaſon, ſhould ſo wickedly belye the principles of it, to ſo infinite a conſequent of abſurdities. For if Princes be <hi>Kings, Lords, Fathers, Heads, &amp;c:</hi> to the ſingle perſons of the Subject only, and not to the univerſality of them, then is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſingle Subject by himſelfe alone a body politique, whereof the King, as King, is Head, and ſo hath as many Kingdomes as Subjects: &amp; every one being diſtinct in relation one from the other, have not, nor can have any civill communion among them; neither can any of them have to doe with the civill Affaires one of another. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (which is not only falſe, but deſtructive to the publique weale
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:197172:5"/> and ſafety of all Kingdomes) If Kings be not Heades of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique community of their People, as well as of the private particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of them, then is the publique community out of the Kings Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and Kings are diſcharged of all care of the publique. For the mutuality of relation betwixt Protection and Subjection, ſuffers not the one to move, but within the limits of the other, and if the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality muſt be under the Kings Protection, it muſt be alſo under His Subjection, for which cauſe the ancient and conſtant wiſedome of our Peers and Commons ſitting in Parliament as the Body repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of the whole Subject of the Kingdome, doe in the Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their Acts, in that quality, to this day, recite themſelves His <hi>Majeſties loyall and faithfull Subjects.</hi> So that in this point the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervour inſolently controules the Wiſedome and Iudgement of the repreſentative of the whole Kingdome, as well as contradicts the principles of reaſon.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, whereas he ſaith that Treaſon ſo farre as it concernes the Prince, is not ſo horrid in nature as oppreſſion in a Prince. Without excuſing any way or diminiſhing the faults of Princes, in any the leaſt act of oppreſſion, let every one but aske his owne conſcience, whether is more horrid in nature, Superiors to wrong Inferiours, or Inferiours their Superiours: Maiſters their Servants, or Servants their Maſters: Husbands their Wives, or Wives their Husbands: Fathers their children, or children their Fathers: and he will ſoon find the impiety of this aſſertion. And whereas now the Obſervor profeſſeth his good will and affection to Monarchy. You may by theſe grounds which he hath laid, and by his propounding to us for a patterne to our Kings, the condition of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and for our Kingdome, the patterne of the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice,</hi> know how falſe a meaning he hath, and what his deſigne is; even to looſen the ſacred tye of Obedience toward our Liege Soveraigne, and with it the firme and ſetled ſtability of the Kingdome, and to prepare mens hearts and perſwaſions, to the receiving of ſome new forme of Government, according to the fancy of the common People.</p>
            <p>Having therefore with falſe principles endeavoured to found the originall of all Soveraignty in the People, as hoping thereby to find meanes to pluck it out of the Kings hands: he then proceeds to perſwade, that not only naturall reaſon, but even the frame of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:197172:6"/> Kingdome, and the poſitive lawes thereof, doe all concurr to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the higheſt Soveraignty to be in the People. But when he ſhould make that apparent by the manifeſt Iudgement and Acts of our Law; not being able to doe that, he ſeekes by ſly inſinuations, to have that admitted and ſwallowed, which to prove he knowes were impoſſible. Therefore pretending to ſhew the originall, the progreſſe, and changes of ſoveraigne government, all from, and by the authority of the People, even from the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. when it ſhould be expected he ſhould ſhew the Soveraignty of this Kingdome to be deriued from them, he runnes himſelfe into a puzle, and then breakes off and tells us what he thinks, and he thinks, that <hi>when moſt Countries have found out an Art and peaceable order for publique Aſſemblies, whereby the people may aſſume its own power, to doe it ſelfe right, without diſturbance to it ſelfe, or injury to Princes; he were unjuſt that would oppoſe that art and order. That Princes may not be beyond all limits of Law, nor tryed upon them by private parties, the whole Community in its underived</hi> Majeſty, <hi>ſhall convene to doe Iustice, &amp;c:</hi> and ſo he goes on inſinuating, that our Parliaments are ſuch publique Aſſemblies, wherein the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in underived Majeſty convenes to doe juſtice upon the King.</p>
            <p>Truly I am not ſo well affected to arbitrary Government, as to admit the judgement (much leſſe the thought of one man) to be proof of Law and Government, We ſhall therefore by Gods helpe examine how well this new conceipt agreeth with our Lawes and auncient ſetled frame of Government. But this is obvious a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, that it is ſo farre from being true that moſt Countries, have found the art and order of <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> wherein the People may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the power of doing themſelves right. As that unleſſe you will call the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of ſome meere popular <hi>Republique,</hi> ſuch an <hi>aſſembly:</hi> there is not the ordinance of any ſuch <hi>aſſembly</hi> to be found in all the world. and the reducing of our Parliaments to ſuch <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,</hi> will ſuit as well, as the ſhaping of our Kingdome to the frame of the common-wealth of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> or of the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we may know therefore that our Parliaments are no ſuch imaginary Aſſemblies, in which the people in underived Majeſty convene to aſſume any Power ſuppoſed to be theirs originally, and with that Power to doe themſelves right. Even the Obſervour himſelfe hath aſſured us, when in his faſt and looſe play, he unawares
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:197172:6"/> confeſſeth that the compoſition of our Parliaments are ſo equall and geometricall, and all parts ſo orderly contribute their office, as that no part can have any extreame predominance over other. This is moſt true that he confeſſeth. God grant that no endeavour to the contrary may ever deprive the Kingdome of the right benefit of this happy and well compoſed Ordinance. But now then if our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be ordained <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> compoſed of three neceſſary different parts, one <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> the others <hi>Subject,</hi> ſome appearing for their own intereſts, others repreſentatively for them that ſent them, and all ballanced in ſuch a geometricall equality, as is proper for the conſervation of their ſeverall rights and intereſts from any extream predominance of one of the parts above the other. Then can they not be aſſemblies of reſumption of the peoples ſuppoſed power, for in ſuch imaginary aſſemblies, there muſt be a diſſolution of all conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute orders, degrees, and qualities of the parts, and all the members muſt be reduced to a naturall coequality undiſtinguiſhed by any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, of quality, degree or priviledges whatſoever: ſo as there muſt be neither King, nor Peers, nor any office or power of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer State remaining, but all reſolved into a meere Chaos, till all be new framed by the deity of the people. So farre therefore are our Parliaments from the nature of ſuch aſſemblies, as that the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of introducing of ſuch Aſſemblies is moſt ſeditious, traiterous, and deſtructive, not only to the perſon and dignity of the King, to the Crowne Imperiall and to the Kingdome it ſelfe (whoſe well ballanced rights have (beſide other tyes) beene ſo often, ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely, and by ſo many of us, even by our whole repreſentative body ſworne to be defended) but even to the rights, priviledges, and being, of the bleſſed Ordinance of our Peace and well-fare our very Parliaments themſelves.</p>
            <p>For we muſt know, that our law (taking notice, that in every State, there are three parties capable of juſt or unjuſt Soveraignty; that is to ſay, ſome Prince; the Nobles; and the People) judged no government ſo ſafe and aſſured, as where every of the three parties capable of Soveraignty, were in ſome ſort admitted to a participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, but ſo admitted, as that ſtill the Soveraignty ſhould cleerly remaine to Him that ought to be the Soveraigne. And to this end, our law (having firſt through the piety of our law-giving Princes obtained a juſt &amp; regular courſe of government; the ſtability where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:197172:7"/> it found to be more concerned in the power of making lawes, then in any other power belonging to the Soveraigne) did for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting innovations that might ſubvert that ſetled regularity: in ſuch a ſort eſtabliſh the frame of State and government, as that the Prince ſhould have his hands bound up from uſing the legiſlative power without the concurrence of the Peers and Commons. But then, to the end that they (whoſe conſent was brought in only to prevent the evill which abſolute power might worke againſt the ſetled frame of the State) might not themſelves become that evill, which they were called to prevent: The Law gave to them no more intereſt in the legiſlative power then it had ſtill left in the hands of the <hi>Prince,</hi> to wit, to every of the three parties, the King, the Peers, and the Commons, an equall power of aſſent or diſſent in making of new Law. And ſo by oppoſing the ſingle power of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them, to the votes of every other two; made ſo ſecure a ballancing of their powers one againſt another; as that no practice of any two of them can doe any thing to the prejudice or diminution of the third, without that third party it ſelfe doe give conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t unto it.</p>
            <p>Nor did the providence of the Law here reſt. But conſidering that in the power of making Lawes it had now oppoſed the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of two numerous bodies, againſt the power of the ſingle Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. It foreſaw, and feared that by the Soveraignes conſenting to Lawes for the eaſe and benefit of the Subject, things might paſſe to the prejudice and diminution of the ſoveraignty, if the ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſoveraigne (ſurcharged with the care of the manifold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Kingdome) ſhould be left all alone to adviſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute His Right againſt all the wiſedome and ſollicitation of the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous body of the Subject. To prevent that: it ordained, that the King ſhould at His owne diſcretion ſweare unto Himſelfe a body of Councell, to adviſe Him in the concernements of His Soveraigne Rights, and ſafety (which is His Privy-Councell) and a body of Councell at law, to adviſe Him that He may neither doe, nor ſuffer contrary to the rule of Law. And through this even Counter-poiſe &amp; ballance of all the three States of Parliament (as through a meanes wherewith God hath eſpecially bleſſed us above other Lands) doe we enjoy the aſſurance of a regular freedome, under the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a juſt and legitimate ſoveraignty. In which, if without the free concurrence of every of the three ordained parties, there ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:197172:7"/> be any invaſion and exerciſe of the legiſlative power; then ſhall the well ballanced frame of legitimate law-making be overthrowne, and with it, the rightfull being and uſe of Parliaments deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>But the Obſervor having not aſcribed ſuch underived Majeſty to Aſſemblies of the Community, to the end to maintaine the rights of Parliaments, but to innovate Parliaments to the deſtruction of their true being, and to the transformation of the State and government. Howſoever that <hi>fol.</hi> 15. he tells us only of ſome defects in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that might receive amendment: yet let's he ſlip, that thoſe Defects, are Diviſions betweene the two Houſes, and betweene the King and them. Now Diviſion being almoſt inevitable, and power of diſſenting neceſſary for ballancing the three differing parts of Parliament, to prevent this power of diſſenting, were to deſtroy the ballance and being of Parliaments, and to make them Courts of popularity, where they that pleaſe the People ſhould abſolutely car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry all things. Though therefore he here diſcovers his deſigne, yet being aſſured not to bring it about, but by miſleading the moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and well-affected both to true eſtabliſhed Religion &amp; Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, He covertly purſues His purpoſe altogether under the ſhew of vindicating the Rights, Priviledges, &amp; being of Parliaments.</p>
            <p>So, whereas our Parliaments are aſſemblies wherein the whole State in three diſtinct formall parts convenes in Councell, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every of thoſe three parts have free power of allowing or diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of any thing propounded for a law, and wherein the law ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth notice of no vote, nor act, for any generall law, ſave what doth paſſe with concurrence of all the three parts of the Aſſembly, The Obſervor tells us, that for the King to ſay, that <hi>without the Kings concurrence and conſent, Parliaments are without all power, this at one blow confounds all Parliaments, and ſubjects us to as unbounded a Regiment of the Kings will, as any Nation under Heaven ever ſuffered under.</hi> And his reaſon is, If Kings may ſo fruſtrate Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, He may by the ſame meanes fruſtrate all inferiour Courts, &amp; then farewell Law, Right, Liberty, and all things. <hi>O impudence!</hi> does His Majeſty in this claime more, then either the Houſe of Peers to it ſelfe, or the Houſe of Commons to it ſelfe challengeth? Nay, claimes His Majeſty more then He acknowledgeth due by the Law to each of the two Houſes, as well as to Himſelfe, freely to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or diſaſſent to what is propounded for a Law, and doe not, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:197172:8"/> have not, both they and His Majeſty and both their Predeceſſours ever practiſed that power? ſo as we have had ſcarce one Parliament wherein either King or Peers, or Commons (or perhaps every one of them) have not ſeverally diſſented from the votes each of other two and tye their diſſent fruſtrated the votes of the other two, and yet (God be praiſed) our Parliaments doe, and (we hope) ſtill ſhall continue, notwithſtanding ſuch <hi>undermining foxes</hi> would bring that three fold Cord of our State, into the ſingleſtring of a popular Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and all things ſo into confuſion?</p>
            <p>And how falſe is the conſequence that if the King by diſſenting may make voyd, the ſentence of the two Houſes of Parliament He may alſo voyd the ſentence of any inferiour Court of Iuſtice? When in Parliament, the law hath appointed the King Himſelfe to give His owne Vote and conſent, perſonally if He will, or by His Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters under His great Seale, if He will. But in inferiour Courts hath appointed none to give ſentence or Iudgement but only thoſe Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges who in a definite and formall way are ordained to be the only Miniſters and Deliverers of the Kings Iuſtice and Iudgement in that behalfe, ſo as no perſonall or inſtrumentall aſſent or diſſent of the Kings, can alter or fruſtrate the ſentence or judgement of any infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Court, becauſe that though the Iudges there give the Kings Iudgement, and not their owne; yet the Law having authorized none but them to be the givers of the Kings Iudgement there, it taketh no notice of any other judgement in thoſe Courts, then only of the ſworne Iudges themſelves, and though the King, the Peers, and Commons in Parliament have every one the power, by any one of their votes to fruſtrate the votes of two of them, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming the Iudgement of the whole Court: yet cannot the Vote of either the King, the Peers, or Commons alone, or of any two of them, fruſtrate or change the Iudgement of any inferiour Court. And it is further to be obſerved that in thoſe Courts the Iudges judge as ſtrangers of matters that concernes others only and not themſelves and therefore render Iudgement <hi>in invitum,</hi> againſt the will of one of the parties at leaſt, in which caſe becauſe <hi>expedit rei publica ut finis ſit litium,</hi> if all the Iudges agree not, yet Iudgement ſhall be given according to the Iudgement of the Major part.</p>
            <p>But now (contrary to the uſe of inferiour Courts) The parties in Parliament in (thoſe things that concerne the publique) meddle
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:197172:8"/> not as meere Iudges, but as Parties intereſſed, with things that concerne every of their owne Rights, in which caſe it is neither Law nor reaſon, that ſome of the Parties ſhould determine of that that concernes all their mutuall intereſts, <hi>invitâ altera parte,</hi> againſt the will of any one of the Parties. But that all Parties concurre, or elſe their mutuall intereſt to remaine in the ſame condition it was before, For Parties cannot meddle with Iudging <hi>in invitum,</hi> but <hi>per conſenſum,</hi> and therefore no major part of the three Parties in <hi>Parliament,</hi> but the conſent of all three, muſt make the judgement of that Court, otherwiſe two of the three Parties, may totally or in part oppreſſe the third, and then one of thoſe two, oppreſſe the other, and be a ſole arbitrary Tyrant. The King and Peers may op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Commons; the King and Commons, may oppreſſe the Peers, the Peers and Commons may oppreſſe the King: and then the Peers being eaſily ſuppreſſed by the Commons, what ſhall hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but that ſome <hi>Appian decemvirate</hi> (that under ſhew of zeale of reforming Church and Common-wealth, may carry the ſound and well-affected Subject with them) After they ſhall have not only poſſeſſed mens mindes with the lawfulnes of their authority, but poſseſsed themſelves of the <hi>Militia</hi> &amp; all the Power of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and two or three yeare kept all that power in their hands, pretending they cannot ſooner perfect their Lawes of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (though indeed they doe but time it out, till they ſecure all unto their private ends) (as <hi>Appius</hi> in all things did) what then (I ſay) ſhall hinder, but that by meanes of ſome ſuch <hi>decemvirate</hi> among the Commons, ſome <hi>Appius</hi> may invade an abſolute Soveraignty over us, or miſſing that, reſolve yet all our ſetled State, into an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure troubleſome <hi>Ariſtocracy?</hi> or <hi>Republique?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The better to prepare the way to ſome ſuch upſhot. The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervor findes a defect in the frame of our State, he cannot ſee how <hi>Parliaments</hi> can have ſufficient power, to reſtraine Tyranny, if they can doe no Act without the Kings conſent. And he findes, that if <hi>Princes</hi> in matters that concerne the publique, be admitted to preferre weake opinions (as he calls them) before Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary motives, then <hi>Parliaments</hi> are vaine, <hi>Princes</hi> unlimitable, and Subjects miſerable.</p>
            <p>The Obſerver will be more wiſe and faithfull then the Law it ſelfe, and looking only one way, tells us of inſufficient proviſion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:197172:9"/> for reſtraint of regall power, without ſome coercive ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant be placed over it. But the law that lookes every way, tells us, that the erecting of ſuch a ſuperintending power, would unſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne our King, and make that ſuperintending power Soveraign and when it were made, the exerciſe of it would be ſubject to more dangerous extravagances then regall power is, and yet leſſe capable of regulation then it. Therefore the law (knowing that there is none but God, <hi>qui cuſtodiat ipſos custodes,</hi> that can reſtraine ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Governours, and knowing that nothing in this world can be reduced to ſo abſolute a perfection of ſetledneſſe, but that in the laſt meanes it muſt meerly depend upon the providence of God) after a full conſideration of the weakneſſe and imperfection of every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall forme of Government, concludes, that the Soveraignty was better placed in the hands of a ſole Prince, then in a popular, or Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocraticall hand, and that a poſitive knowne law, without any coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive ſuperintendant, was a ſufficient and the beſt boundary of regall power, againſt any irregularity whatſoever, eſpecially when the law (being backed with a Parliament of all the orders of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) ſhall thereby find meanes of diſcovery and manifeſtation, both of the truth of the law it ſelfe, and likewiſe of the violation of it. For the law, and the tranſgreſſion of the law, being both at once made manifeſt and notorious, that will ſo ſufficient a ſecurity of the future obſervance of the law, as Princes will not further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to violate it; becauſe (as the Poet ſaies)
<q>
                  <l>Nec pueros coram populo Medea trucidat,</l>
                  <l>Aut humana palam coquit exta nefarius Atreus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Infamous acts will not endure to be committed in the ſight of all the world.</p>
            <p>Therefore to ſay truth the Obſervor's conceipt of having ſome ſuperiour power to enforce the law that ſhould regulate the power of the Soveraigne Prince, is a meere falſe conception, of an heart as traiterous to God as to his <hi>Prince,</hi> who would have abſolute ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by an arme of fleſh, when no ſuch can be given to it. For, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate his <hi>Prince,</hi> he would not only have a law, but a ſuperiour power to enforce that law; and ſuch a ſuperiour power being once erected, that muſt alſo be either boundleſſe, or muſt be circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with a law: if circumſcribed with a law, then alſo muſt that law have a ſuperiour coercive power, to enforce it, and ſo muſt we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:197172:9"/> have ſuperiour Power, over ſuperiour Power, <hi>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad infinitum,</hi> and yet at laſt, leave the moſt ſuperiour power, in that liberty which the Obſervour calleth boundleſſe, arbitrary, and tyrannicall. And how abſurd a thing is it to imagine, That when the Law hath truſted the ſoveraigne Power in the hands of the King, it ſhould again diſtruſt Him and unſoveraigne Him, and place in another the ſoveraignty of the ſame ſoveraign Truſt? and with a ſecond abſurdity leave in the Kings hand the Power of calling together and diſſolving the power whereby He himſelfe ſhould be conſtrained? and (to make up all) ſhould by authority of that power, conſtrain all the Heads of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and even the repreſentative body of that power, by ſolemne oath, to declare that the King is not only <hi>Supream</hi> Governour, but that He is the <hi>only Supream</hi> Governour, when (ſuch a ſuperiour power admitted) he can be neither only, nor at all, Supream.</p>
            <p>But the Obſervour aiming more to ſubvert what is eſtabliſhed, then to reduce things unto their firſt eſtabliſhment, quarrels ſtill with the Regall power; and he reaſons, that whether or no the Law gives the ſingle Perſon of the Prince as full and free a Vote to aſſent or not aſſent, as it doth to either the Houſe of Peers or Houſe of Commons, yet is not the Prince to uſe the liberty of His Vote licentiouſly, but adviſedly and by Councell, and what Councell can He have more wiſe, faithfull and impartiall, then theirs that repreſent the whole Kingdom, who cannot be ſuppoſed to have private ends as Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Cavaliers, and private men may have?</p>
            <p>Truly that Princes ought with great reſpect to hearken to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and information of the great Councell of the body of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who can ſo much as make a queſtion of it? But why ſhould theſe things be objected to His Majeſty? For what Prince of all his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors hath ſo much harkened &amp; condeſcended to his great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, as His Majeſty at once hath done unto this preſent Parliament? Not any one; Nay, not the whole ſucceſſion of His predeceſſors ſince the granting of the great Charter hath done the like. Witneſſe the condeſcending to the Earle of <hi>Staffords</hi> attainder, the damning of Ship-mony, and of all Monopolies, the Star-Chamber, and high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Court, the taking away of the Votes of Biſhops &amp; of Popiſh Lords, the parting with the long uſed power of impoſing upon mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, bounding of Forreſts, and yeelding to the regulation of whatſoever further greivance ſhould be found in the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:197172:10"/> And (for a ſeale of obſervance of all) the granting of a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enniall Parliament, and the perpetuating of this preſent Parliament. With what diſpenſation of the violating of Chriſtianity can a Subject (through all theſe preſumptions to the contrary) charge his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne with averſnes to publique counſell, and inclination to private whi perers? O that being at once poſſeſt of ſo many not long ſince unhoped for ſatisfactions, we might not want hearts to enjoy them and acknowledge them.</p>
            <p>But the two Houſes thought the Kingdome in imminent danger, and deſired it ſhould be put in a poſture of defence, and His Majeſty by evill Counſell refuſed and deſerted them. Truly the Obſervour neither doth nor can ſhew, that His Majeſty, upon the Parliaments apprehenſion of danger, refuſed to take order for the defence of the Kingdom; for the contrary thereof is true. And in His ſeeking to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it by a military poſture, He ſo farre condeſcended to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of His <hi>Parliament,</hi> as that He offered to change the perſons, that in any County had the charge of the <hi>Militia,</hi> if His <hi>Parliament</hi> made any juſt exception to any of them. And for His <hi>Maieſties</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> even in that alſo He ſo farre hearkned to them as that he offered, that if, to ſecure future ſeditions, they would make ſome exemplar puniſhment of the Actors in the late <hi>ſeditious Tumults there,</hi> He would even come thither. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refuſed in that: He notwithſtanding, offered them to come to any other indifferent place. As for the place where they now ſit, who (that hath vowed His Faith to the Lawes of the Land, and to the Priviledge of <hi>Parliament</hi>) can in ſuch conſcience as He will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer God withall, hold that a place of indifference and of freedom to vote in, where the people in <hi>Tumult</hi> demanded of the Houſe of Commons to know who were the Lords that refuſed to vote with them, and where ſome of the <hi>Peers</hi> were aſſaulted by the multitude for having differed in their votes from them, and yet none of thoſe <hi>Tumulters</hi> were puniſhed or ever queſtioned for it?</p>
            <p>But ere we leave this point of hearkning to the advice of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider too, that though we grant it behoovefull for the King to hearken to His Parliament, we muſt not underſtand it ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoovefull, as that there ſhould be inevitable neceſſity laid upon Him, that He muſt follow whatſoever they adviſe, for then at one blow we overthrow the fundamentall Law &amp; frame of Parliaments.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:197172:10"/> If from any of the three formall parts of the Parliament we take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the freedome of voting, to aſſent or diſſent, we breake the threefold cord of the State, we caſt away the ballance of it, &amp; even diſſolve the very frame it ſelfe. If when for neceſſity of State, the Head aſſembles the whole body in Counſell, (where the Law gives the Head one vote of three, and allowes Him a Body of Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to maintain the proper Rights of the Head) the Head may not uſe that Power which the Law giveth it, no not in caſe the two other partes conteſt &amp; claime part of the Right belonging to the Head, &amp; where (by Law) the Vote of the Head is oppoſed in ballance, to the moderation of thoſe two powers; as well as their powers are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ballance to the power of the head; but that the Head muſt do all things according to the advice &amp; counſell of the two parts, which are the body of the Subject. Then all that ſolemne forme of Law, that calleth the Head, Soveraign: that authoriſeth the Head to ſwear a body of Privy Councell; to convoke the Nobles and Commons in publique Counſell; to call to that Counſell whom He thinker good: to take homage of the Peers, and Oath of Supreamacy of the Commons: and having uſed their Counſell, at His Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſſolve it. All this (I ſay) is then a meer miſleading for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of the law, The Soveraignty (againſt all our Oathes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to the contrary) is not in the King but in the people; the King is the only Subject, and but a common vouchee, whoſe concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is unavoidably implyed; His will, his underſtanding, and his power (though he be acknowledged Head, Soveraigne, and chief reſidence of authority) is all ſubjected to the body of the very Subject that in Parliament doth ſweare ſubjection to Him. The tripartite frame of a Parliament of three Eſtates, is a vaniſhing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition: there is really nothing but a meer popular aſſembly, not of Subjects but Soveraignes. The Crowne Imperiall and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe, (though aſſerted by our ſolemneſt Acts of Recogniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and oathes of the body repreſentative,) are meer <hi>non entia,</hi> we are but a Republique, and the chief Head of the Kingdome hath not (beſide the name) more of a King, then the Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> or the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> And this being hid ever ſince the firſt beginning of the Kingdome; the whole generation of the Subject ever ſince, hath by the injury of our Lawes, been moſt impiouſly miſ-worne in their allegiance; and the errour hath never been diſcovered till the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:197172:11"/> whole Kingdome (having now ſolemnly ſworne to ſtand to, and defend the Lawes) cannot receade from their wrong-ſworn obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but with the guilt of univerſall perjury, and under the burthen of that guilt, expoſe an old grown Kingdom, to the hazards of a new framed Common-wealth. All this does neceſſarily follow, if we take away the freedome of the Kings aſſent and diſſent in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> or barre Him of the uſe of His Counſells advice therein.</p>
            <p>I ſhould little need to ſay any thing concerning that which the Obſervour ſo much pretends that Communities, and univerſalities of men, are voyd of corrupt affections and of private ends, and that therefore their deſires are alwayes luſt, and their councell faithfull and impartiall. But when in the fallacy of this perſwaſion there lyes (I fear) a great part of the ſinne, for which Gods anger now ſo publiquely doth ſhew it ſelfe upon us, I would be loath to paſſe it over without any touch at all. I feare we are too diffident to reſt upon the ordinance of God: I feare we are too confident of our ſelves, as if our owne naturall providence (if we were left unto it) were beyond any other meanes of ſafety, although it were the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God unto us. A word or two ſhall not therefore be unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary concerning the corruptions &amp; errors that even communities themſelves are often ſubject to.</p>
            <p>That Communities are leſſe ſubject to private ends and affections then particular men are, is true: but it is alſo true, that they are not abſolutely free from them, and when they fall into them, they are more fatally violent and dangerous. And though one would think it repugnant, that an univerſality (which conteines the whole pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique) ſhould have private ends; or that that ſhould any way be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted private, which they that conteine the publique doe purſue: yet ſeeing it is not the number of agents, but the capacity in which they act, the quality of their acting, and the coherence or incoherence of what they purſue, with the publiques end and weale; that makes the actions of men publique or private: it muſt needs follow, that if without authority, or out of the way of the publique ordinance, men purſue any thing (though the whole community concurre in the purſuit) yet is all of the nature of a private action, done to a corrupt and private end, for though the thing intended be to the preſent good of the publique, yet being beſide the ordinance and way, it is in conſequence againſt the good and weale of the publique, &amp; ſo againſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:197172:11"/> the very ends of the publique. And as in the body naturall a very few members (that is none but the eyes) have the ſenſe of ſeeing, but all the members have the ſenſe of feeling. ſo in Communities all have the ſence of enjoying good, or ſuffering evill: but very few the faculty of diſcerning the cauſe and means of either. Yet the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of the Community (more carried by ſenſe then true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning) oft makes the judgement of the whole Community, and brings it to act that, that agreeth not with the intended weale of the Comity. By this means (at the beſt) the whole univerſality of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (contrary to their own finall good and proſperity) forced their Prieſt to ſet them up golden Calves. By this meanes the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of them againe revolted from <hi>David</hi> (their King by Gods immediate Ordination) to <hi>Abſolom</hi> an uſurper. By this means the univerſality of the tenne Tribes, for redreſſe of their grievances, rebelled againſt <hi>Davids</hi> Grand-child, and ſet up <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving their own affected falſe religion, authorized that ſinne which purſued them in their extirpation. It is therefore an untruth, to ſay that Communities can have no private ends, and a belying of the Law and Truth to ſay (as fol. 22.) that ever there was ſuch a <hi>Maxime.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid, that though in Communities the body at large (in which the vulgar is the greateſt part) may be ſubject to corrupt affections and ends; yet the body repreſentative, which is the Choice of the Community, is to be preſumed free from corrupt ends and affections, and therefore moſt wiſe, faithfull, and aſſured.</p>
            <p>Truly we pray, that ſince in this knot lye many ſcruples that wring the conſciences of thouſands in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we may with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt freedom, reaſon the things that tend to clearing the honour and obſervance due to repreſentatives. To whom we acknowledge the higheſt honour and obſervance that can be given to the body repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. But the honour and authority of the repreſentative will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies depend upon two things, that is, the quality and condition of the body repreſented, and the quality of the repreſentation it ſelfe: for as that is more or leſſe proper and lively, ſo will it derive more or leſſe authority and reputation. If therefore the body at large be an abſolute free ſoveraigne (as is the Community of a right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique) the true repreſentative of that body is then to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with all ſoveraigne honour and due ſubjection: but if the body
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:197172:12"/> at large be it ſelfe a Subject, the honour and authority of the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative cannot exceed the honour and authority of a Subject: for none can make their image more then they themſelves are. Next then, (beſides that all repreſentations how plenarily ſoever autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, muſt ever be ſubject to the condition of the body repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) The repute and authority of repreſentatives, will alſo follow the ſoundneſſe or weakneſſe, exactneſſe or imperfection of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation it ſelfe. For if throughout an whole Community the repreſenters be equally and proportionably ordained according to the true relative intereſt, that each part which ſendeth them hath to the whole publique (as in the united Provinces they are) there will be all full acknowledgement of authority to the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that poſſibly can be to the body at large: and there will alſo be ſome preſumption that the repreſenters are authorized, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſoveraignly of thoſe things that concerne the publique. But if (on the other ſide) there be no equality, in making repreſenters, obſerved: but that ſome parts ſend as many as others that are an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times greater and more conſiderable, both in power and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of burthen in the Commonwealth and if for ſome of the parts none are admitted to chooſe the repreſenters, but ſubſtantiall legall Freeholders, and for other parts all are admitted of what condition ſoever. And if the number of thoſe that are unproportionably and promiſcuouſly choſen, doe three or foure fold, exceed the number of them that are ſtrictly choſen for the moſt principall part of the Community. And laſtly, if it lye in the power of ſome other autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to give to ſome particular Townes the power of ſending repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, equall in number to the greateſt Provinces of the Community. Theſe circumſtances will not only detract from the repute and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that a more exact repreſentative of the Community might have, but vehemently demonſtrate that the inſtitution and end of ſuch a repreſentative is rather to miniſter information of the ſtate and condition of every of thoſe particular places and advice, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to ſome other ſoveraigne, and to conſent with him, then to determine ſoveraignly it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>To come then to the Objection of the aſſuredneſſe of Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives in their judgement and fidelity. If in Kingdoms, we by the repreſentative body of the Community meane a perfect repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the whole body Politique, ſo as that the head as well as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:197172:12"/> the other parts doe freely cooperate and concurre (as in our Acts of Parliament it ever doth) then can we preſume no other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile more aſſuredly wiſe, faithfull, or ſafe for the publique, then is the counſaile of the univerſall repreſentative in that ſenſe. But if by the repreſentative, we mean the repreſentation of the groſſe of the body without the head, (that is, the repreſentative of the body of the Subject only) then is the aſſertion falſe, for the Law preſumes not in the repreſentative of the Subject, ſo aſſured judgement and fidelity for government, as it doth in the ſoveraigne head alone, for then it would not have placed the ſoveraignty in the head, but in the repreſentative of the groſſe of the body. But the Law knowing both Communities themſelves, ſubject to dangerous inclinations from private incitements, and their repreſentatives likewiſe ſubject to miſleadings, factions and ambitions of private men, hath (as in the moſt aſſured place, placed the ſoveraignty in the head, and the head ſo having the ordinance, both for judgement and for government, where the ordinance is, there is the bleſſing and there the beſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance.</p>
            <p>We need not ſeek examples how repreſentative bodies of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects moving without conſent of their head have been miſled: there is not one imitable example to be found that ever the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Subject, moved to act ſoveraignly without the conſent of the head. But we have examples of ſoveraigne repreſentatives, in Republiques themſelves, notoriouſly miſled by private men; was there ever a more reverend repreſentative then the Roman Senate, yet did not <hi>Appius</hi> and his Faction, under the Colour of a <hi>Dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> (or Comittee of reformation) ſo blind that Senate, as to work them to conferre all the power of the Commonwealth into his, and his Factious hands, to the ſubverſion of the common liberty? ſo as that if by accident he had not been taken away, he had made himſelfe Prince? And was not that ſoveraigne repreſentative, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time wholly ſwayed and caried by <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Sulpitius?</hi> Sure as nothing is more wholſome for the publique, then that the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne of a Kingdom ſhould often have the advice of the body repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of the Community, ſo is it moſt dangerous for the publique to have the advice of the Community enforced on the Soveraigne. Leaſt ſo that that ſhould be for Our good, be unto us an occaſion of falling.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:197172:13"/>
            <p>But the Obſervour inſiſts not ſo much, that the repreſentative bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is the great Councell of the King and Kingdom: as that it is the ſupream judge and the moſt ſoveraigne power. If the Prince (ſaith he) be ſeduced, ſome Court muſt judge of the ſeducement, and ſome power enforce that judgement , and that muſt be the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (meaning the two houſes of Parliament.)</p>
            <p>We have already ſhewed the abſurdity of a ſuperior power to enforce the Soveraigne: but farther to diſſolve all difficulties in this falſe aſſertion, we muſt know that in Parliament there are diverſe kinds of judgements. And that the meer repreſentative body, that is, the houſe of Commons ſolely, hath not any judicatory power by it ſelfe, unleſſe it be in particular caſes concerning their own houſe and members. But they are as the great Inqueſt of the Kingdom to enquire, diſcover, impeach, &amp;c. The houſe of Peeres hath general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all things judgement preparatory in order to judgement of Parliament, as to give Oath, to take recogniſance, to fine, to impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp;c. In matters that come before them bywrit of Error, it hath judgement <hi>deciſive</hi> to determine and adjudge Law. But this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it hath not as it is part of the repreſentative body: for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative body hath not therein any part with it. But the houſe of Peeres alone hath this ſuperior judgement, as great Court of the Kings Barons of the Kingdom, which being aſſiſted with the Iudges of all the Benches, is by formall Ordinance of Law in all matters ſo coming before it, the proper and immediat ſuperior Iudge of Law. But it is not abſolute ſupreme Iudge of Law in all things: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot revoke the judgement which it ſelfe hath given. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can the Houſe of Commons, nor the two houſes together re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke, or anull any judgement given in the Houſe of Peeres, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; therefore alſo the two Houſes are not ſupream judges or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarers of Law. The <hi>Obſerver</hi> (fol. 44.) tells you the reaſon, To be ſupream judge or declarer of Law is all one as to be ſupream maker of Law, and that you know the two Houſes are not. But in the whole three Eſtates of Parliament, that is, in the King, the Peeres and Commons, there and there only are all powers ingredient, for they upon Bill are not only judges of the laſt reſort, to reverſe the judgement of the Houſe of Peeres and of inferior Courts, but they can repeale and reſtore, and repeale againe <hi>in infinitum</hi> their own Iudgements and Acts. And they can not only declare the Law but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:197172:13"/> they can make the law, and none but they. They alone are they that cannot be bound by precedents or Acts of Parliament, they alone are they that have the Legiſlative Power: and therefore they, and only they that have the abſolute Supream Iudgement of the Law.</p>
            <p>But (ſaith the Obſerver) <hi>The King deſerts His Parliament,</hi> imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that then the two houſes muſt be Supream judges; though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they were not. As well may he imply, that if the King come not to Parliament then are the two Houſes no more Subiects, but So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign's, yea Soveraign's in the higheſt exaltation. Let us ſee what this deſerting is, that ſhall ſo eaſily create Soveraignty in Subiects. We know that by the law, the Kings perſonal preſence is of no abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity to the proceedings of Parliament, and that by the law (declared and confirmed 33. <hi>Hen:</hi> 8.21.) the Kings preſence is not neceſſary at His giving conſents to Acts paſſed, but He may give conſent in His abſence by His great Seale. If then the Law count His perſonall abſence no deſerting: and as to deſerting for want of iuſt and reaſonable conſent to their demands, His Maieſty be ſo little faulty toward this Parliament, as that he hath given His Conſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the example of His Predeceſſours. Where then ſhall a ſincere Conſcience in any deſerting the King hath made, finde warrant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to deſert this Soveraign, and acknowledge another Superiour? but to return.</p>
            <p>Diverſity of Powers and authorities exerciſed in the ſeverall parts of Parliament, neceſſarily cauſes a diverſity of reſpect and obſervance to be rendred to them. And though the iudgement of the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative of the Subiect (that is of the Peers and Commons) in thoſe things wherein it is properly exerciſed, ought to have eſteem and credit before any other iudgement of the Subiect. Yet is it not to be oppoſed to the iudgement of the Soveraigne, in thoſe things which the law hath entruſted to the iudgment of the Soveraign for the law truſteth none but whom it iudgeth to have judgment, fidelity, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of all neceſſary incidents ſufficient for that truſt and then it preferrs both the Acts and iudgement, of the party truſted, before any other iudgement whatſoever. Not is the iudgment of the whole Kingdome any whit ſlighted thereby, no more then if in particular Sciences (as Divinity, Philoſophy, Phyſick, Mathematique, &amp;c.) the iudgement of the profeſſors of thoſe Sciences ſhould be preferred before the iudgement of the whole body repreſentative, for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuique
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:197172:14"/> in ſua arte credendum:</hi> Matters of State and ſecrets of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are not only unfit and dangerous to be publiquely managed, by ſo numerous a body as our repreſentative is, but the greater part are ſo little experienced or able to manage them as that in <hi>Edw.</hi> the thirds time, the Houſe of Commons themſelves (as the Obſervour (fol. 6. tell us) deſired they might be ſpared from giving advice in thoſe matters, <hi>de queuxals nont pas cognizance,</hi> of which they had not the Cogniſans. The Iudgement of the body repreſentative it ſelfe, did not at that time beleive, but that aſwell the Iudgement, as the care of the <hi>Ardua Regni,</hi> did cheifly belong to the King. To whom alone, the Law having committed the Soveraign Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ordained him withall, a body of ſworn privy Councell to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with therein, and a ſworne Counſell at Law to adviſe Him of the Rights and Priviledges, that belong unto Him as ſupream Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, and firſt of the three States of Parliament.</p>
            <p>If any of theſe ſworn Counſailers ſhall Counſaill the King againſt the known Law, or any by their counſaill, act any thing againſt it: after legall proceeding and conviction, it will ſoon be out of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what ſhall become of them. But if without legall proof of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, ſuch Counſailers ſhall by generall vote of the Subject, be ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured private whiſperers and ſeducers of the King, and to be wholly removed from Him: then ſhall the King at once be dangerouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the conſtant meanes which the Law hath eſpecially or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned Him, for ſupport of His Right againſt the other two oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed powers, and for the good diſcharge of His Kingly office. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides if men ſhall ſo be condemned and made guilty, more by Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty and uncontroulablenes of Iudgement aſcribed to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demners, then by clearneſſe of evidence and legall proof of any fact then is the birth-right of the Subiect, in the higheſt concernment of Life and fortunes taken from Him, and He muſtſtand and fall by the vote of the people, that (like a Iudgement infallible) ſhall ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the office of both witnes, Peers, and Iudge.</p>
            <p>While I purſue the examination of thoſe things which the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervour would have received for reaſon, I may not let ſlip the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of his ſlye unfaithfulnes and deceipt, to paſſe over that point which moſt of all concernes the ſoules and bodyes, lives and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of the whole Kingdome, and all becauſe his want of proof in that point, does (if noted) overthrow all that he contends for. For
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:197172:14"/> though he argues the lawfulnes of Subjects taking up Armes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the Authority and Commands of the King, under the warrant of a generall rule to this effect, <hi>That in extream perill and failance of ordinary meanes, any extraordinary meanes may be taken for the ſafety of the People:</hi> yet finding an impoſſibility of proving the State in ſuch extream danger (for indeed ſuch a danger muſt be ſo viſible to all men as not to need any proving) and finding it alſo not poſſible to prove a neceſſity of the Subjects arming himſelfe for want of other meanes, when His <hi>Maieſty,</hi> (in whom the naturall ordinary meanes of protection is placed) readily offered, and yet offers, to performe that regall office of protecting; The Obſervour paſſes over the matter without proving either danger or want of other meanes, and preſſes only the lawfulnes of ſelfe-defence in extreame danger, as if (if that were granted) all men might take up Armes whether there were danger or no, and whether there were other ordinary meanes of defence or no, and ſo ſecurely doe we purſue this errour, as that we with it ſwallow any thing, and becauſe that in ordinary providing for danger before it threaten; the ordinary courſes of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Kingdom in a poſture of defence by Commiſſions of Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancy and of Array, are voted illegall; therefore we not only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to be ſo, but we admit alſo that the King (to whom it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongs to take order for the ſafety of the Kingdome) may not in extreamity of danger, by any meanes that he can uſe, raiſe Armes, and put the Kingdome in a poſture of defence, but the Subject (to whom it is Treaſon (by the Law) to raiſe Forces without autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the King) he may (againſt the ordinary rule of Law) raiſe Armes in the very ſame forme that is unlawfull for the King to doe, and all becauſe of the extream neceſſity and danger. Yet the very ſame neceſſity and danger ſhall not make it lawfull to the Right and proper Authority of the King to doe the very ſame thing. Oh, what ſhall we ſay, when at once, extreame neceſsity is pretended, all wonted formes of defence (without ſhewing a lawfull forme) are declared unlawfull, and the courſe which Law abhorres, and the Conſcience of every Law-ſworne Chriſtian trembles at, is ſet on foot, without the warrant of the lawfull Soveraign, when yet he is ready to ſupply that office in the Iuſt and lawfull way?</p>
            <p>I cannot alſo but note, that though levying of Armes and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Kingdom in a poſture of defence is a right ſo clearly belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:197172:15"/> to the King, as that we know His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> &amp; all His Predeceſſors have ever been poſſeſſed of it as a right and authority inſeperably an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Crown, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> nere any have lawfully exerciſed, but they. And though the repreſentative body of the Kingdom, and (in them) every one of the body repreſented have, according to the poſitive law, ſworn allegiance to the King and ſworn to aſſiſt and defend &amp;c. <hi>all Priviledges, preheminences, and authorities belonging to his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, His heirs and ſucceſſors, or annexed to the Imperiall Crown of the Realm &amp;c.</hi> Yet is not the obſerver afraid to ſay that the Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy is not endangered by ſuch taking of Armes. Nor is he affraid to ſay that next to renouncing of God, nothing under Heaven can be more perfidious then peoples withdrawing themſelves fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations. As if Subjects, by giving authority to ſome of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes to repreſent them, &amp; to adviſe, &amp; conſent for them, gave them a power ſo much above the condition of Subjects, yea ſo much above the condition of their Soveraign, as that neither breach of faith, nor Oath, nor any other duty unto him, were comparable to their with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vote or act of their own repreſenters: as if the right of the King, the Crown, &amp; Kingdom; &amp; the concurrence of the three Eſtates in Parliament, did not ſo concern the Commons of the Land but that, (againſt all) they ſtood ſoly bound in allegiance to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters as to the only Soveraignes of their obedience. Of that it may pleaſe the two honourable Houſes to take into a ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; how repugnant theſe poſitions are to the loyalty of a true Chriſtian: how hard it is for a pious conſcience to perſwade is ſelfe, that they that broach ſuch Doctrines intend nothing but the defence of the King, of the lawes of the Land, and of the true Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: how much the name and Maieſty of God himſelfe is blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, when in a Chriſtian Kingdom that boaſtes it ſelfe of the knowledge and true profeſſion of his word; ſuch Doctrines ſo dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to Chriſtianity ſhould ſo audatiouſly be maintained: And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how much it muſt needs reflect upon their own honour, in poynt of jealouſie and diſtruſt (as if ſome ill-affected factious perſons had too great an influence and power over their votes) when ſuch impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſſertions, ſo deſperatly miſleading the ſoules and conſciences of men, are ſo licentiouſly divulged without any condemnation check, or diſcountenances, from them though earneſtly deſired by His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> at their hands.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:197172:15"/>
            <p>I ſuppoſe there remaines not in the obſervations any thing mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, that is not already anſwered. As for the deſign of changing Religion into Popery, which the obſerver perhaps glances at in ſpeaking of <hi>Popiſh Prelaticall and Military Courtiers.</hi> If a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an can in his conſcience find any other ground for ſuch beleife then only the opinion of a judgement, that would be beleived rather for authorities ſake, then for any thing prooved or diſcovered, he then may well liſten to it. But if inſtead of preſumptions that way, he findes preſumptions of intended change to the contrary Corruption of Religion, a good Conſcience will not be ſo Popiſhly affected, as for the infallibility of any judgement, to beleive contrary to what his heart telleth him the moſt apparent preſumption muſt incline him. For beſides that it is eaſier to bring in a corruption in extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty contrary to an old exploded corruption, then to recover that, that hath been once exploded, (as Popery hath been and is.) We have His <hi>Majesties</hi> often ſolemne atteſtation of God, imprecating the proſperity of Him and His, if he do not maintain the true Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of England againſt all Popery. We have not the like on the other part, againſt Schiſmaticall innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Yet our Schiſmatiques are thrice as many as our Papiſts; and whereas our Papiſts are (God be thanked) diſarmed, awed, and in feare, our Schiſmatiques are bold, armed, and in authority, and therefore licentious, and tumulting in every place.</p>
            <p>God will require an account of our Oathes, and Proteſtations for defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, aswell againſt Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call corruptions, as againſt Popiſh. And an account of our ſolemn Oathes of Supremacy, and of obſervance of the Law, as well againſt popular inſolences, and invaſions of Soveraigne power, as againſt regall Tyranny. Let us take heed, that when <hi>becauſe of Oathes the Land</hi> already <hi>mournes;</hi> we through an univerſall breach of Oathes make it not for perjury mourn more greivouſly. Leaſt when with our ſolemn Oathes, we have brought the animadverſion of our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of Law, of right, and of Religion, before the preſence of God, as Iudge and Revenger of it; and with out own hands kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a fire for the triall of it: we our ſelves be found guilty of a breach, or of halting in it. Let us weigh well the cauſe, the ground, the way, and the end of our taking Armes, that the horror of unjuſt and cauſeleſſe blood-ſhedding may not lye upon us; let us ſee what
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:197172:16"/> it is that we would have, which we may not already have without it.</p>
            <p>May we not after ſome proviſion made for forbearance of ſuch Ceremonies, as by the Iudgement of the Church ſhall be thought fit to be ſpared, have the authorized ſervice of the Church eſtabliſhed? And after purgation and regulation of ſome enormities in Church government, have the diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in a good condition ſetled, with ſevere penall proviſion againſt connivers and Innovators in the one or in the other? Hath not His Majeſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelfe ready and willing to conſent thereto? Againe, to make ſure the aboliſhing of all grievances already ſuppreſt, and to regulate Armes, and ſome other extravagances in government not yet provided for, may we not have fit proviſionary lawes, with ſevere and penall damning of all practices to the contrary? Doth not His Majeſty to that alſo freely offer His conſent? what can be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the ſetling of as ſound and well a governed Church and State, as any Nation under Heaven hath ever lived in? For if by a ſevere Law the perſons of them that ſhall attempt any thing prejudiciall to the ſetled practice of Religion or to the declared liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject be expoſed to exemplary puniſhment, no feare of Innovation to the prejudice of either can remaine. Nor can we feare His <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> tolerating of offenders when beſides his imprecating in that caſe himſelfe and His, he has (in caſe he ſo violates the Law) with His owne mouth diſpenced with His Subjects obedience. As for Our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> it can no way be in the power of the King to take away the leaſt Right, much leſſe the being of <hi>Parliaments;</hi> for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a King can doe to the prejudice of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever averſe He may be from them, yet alwayes the neceſſity of State will at laſt enforce the calling of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and when it is called, it is preſently repoſſeſſed, and re-inveſted of all the Rights and Priviledges that doe belong unto it. For nothing but a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> it ſelfe, or ſo much of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> as in the peoples opinion ſhall have the authority of a whole <hi>Parliament,</hi> can any way deſtroy the being of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or deprive them of the leaſt right or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge belonging to them.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, if they that deviſed and broached the new State principles &amp; doctrines publiſhed in the Book of <hi>Obſervations,</hi> have in them dealt truely and faithfully with the Subject. Then let
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:197172:16"/> the Author of thoſe Doctrines reioyce in them that receive and maintaine them; and let the maintainers of them reioyce in them that were the authors. But if they have dealt unfaithfully and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfully with the ſoules of the Subiect to cauſe the blinde (that cannot Iudge) to erre, thereby to bring to paſſe their own deſigned innovations. Then let it pleaſe the juſt, and all-ſeeing Supream Iudge of Iudges in mercy to ſo many thouſand ſoules in this our <hi>Jſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,</hi> who in the darkneſſe of theſe difficulties know not the right hand from the left, to ſend (as once he did at <hi>Jothams</hi> inſtance) <hi>Iud</hi> 9.16. a fire from the malitious authors of them, to bring to confuſion and ſhame the malignant maintainers and defenders of them; and a fire from them to bring to confuſion the malitious authors. And let the Throne of our Soveraigne Lord the King, (with us the only ſupream Vice-gerent of the great and Supream Iudge) be in righteouſneſſe, in Iudgement, to true Religion, and in Peace for ever eſtabliſhed over us.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>The Printer, to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THis Summary Anſwer (good Reader) having it ſeemes lyen long upon the way to <hi>Oxford,</hi> happned to come to the Preſſe before <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> laſt, where by reaſon of our full imployment ever ſince, Is could not be dispatched till now.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
